"Can NAD+ Boosters Increase
Lifespan and Healthspan?"
The effects of NAD+ boosters
on aged rodents
have been described
in the medical literature
as “profound,” “dramatic”…
“remarkable….”
Treated mice had increased
physical activity, improved vision,
and strengthened bones while
delaying or preventing muscle loss,
hearing loss, cognitive decline,
and ovarian aging.
Benefits to nearly every organ
system have been documented,
including improved artery function,
brain function,
heart function,
immune function,
kidney function, liver function,
and muscle function.
For example, a single week of an
NAD+ booster was sufficient
to restore key markers of muscle
health in a 22-month-old mouse
to levels similar to that
of a 6-month-old mouse.
That’s roughly the equivalent
of reverting the muscle health
of a 70-year-old person back
to when they were just 20.
NAD+ boosters can also extend
the lifespans of animals,
presumed to be due to the elevation
of sirtuin activity dependent on NAD+.
This longevity effect
was first demonstrated
more than 20 years
ago in yeast cells.
An overexpression of the genes
involved in NAD+ synthesis
extended replicative lifespans
by as much as 60%.
In the microscopic
worm C. elegans,
NAD+-boosting compounds
have been shown
to extend lifespans
by up to 16%.
In mice, one NAD+ booster
was able to extend lifespan
by a more modest 5%,
but this was accomplished even when
supplementation was started late in life,
which is unusual for
longevity treatments.
No wonder people are excited about
all manner of NAD+ boosting supplements.
The big question is do any of
these healthspan or lifespan effects
translate to benefiting humans?
There are four major NAD+ boosting
supplements on the market these days:
nicotinic acid (NA),
also known as niacin,
nicotinamide (NAM),
also known as niacinamide,
nicotinamide riboside (NR),
and nicotinamide
mononucleotide (NMN).
NAD+ can also be given directly,
as well as its hydrogenated form NADH.
There are also hydrogenated
forms of NMN and NR,
also known as
dihydronicotinamide riboside.
So, there is quite
the alphabet soup:
NA, NAM, NMN, NR, NAD,
NADH, NMNH, and NRH.
The body can also make
NAD+ “from scratch”
from the amino
acid tryptophan.
Given the critical
nature of NAD+,
it is perhaps unsurprising that the
body has so many different pathways
utilizing a panoply
of precursors.
Converting tryptophan to
NAD+ requires eight steps,
whereas NA, NAM, and NR can be turned
into NAD+ in only two or three steps.
NMN is a direct
precursor of NAD+,
but when NMN or NR is taken orally,
it appears to just turn into NA or NAM,
via rapid degradation
in the bloodstream
or active conversion in the liver.
So, why take the more
expensive NMN or NR
if it’s just going to end
up as NA or NAM?
Bought in bulk, NA or NAM
would just cost pennies a day
versus more like a dollar
a day for NR or NMN.
That would add up to hundreds
of dollars a year for NR or NMN
compared to closer to only five bucks
for a whole year’s worth of NA or NAM.
But cost aside, what are the risks
and benefits of all these NAD boosters?
That’s exactly what I’ll cover, next.